Mss.B.B121 Mss.B.B121
American Philosophical Society
Bache family papers, 1770-1890 (bulk), 1770-1923 (inclusive)
Bulk, 1770-1890
1770-1923 (Bulk 1770-1890)
Mss.B.B121
American Philosophical Society
50.0 Item(s)
The family correspondence of Richard and Sarah Franklin Bache on a variety of topics including references to Benjamin Franklin and his estate. There is also a family genealogy.
50 items.
Bache family
Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
Bache, Catherine Wistar, 1770-1820
Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808
Bache, Theophylact, 1735-1807
Bache, William, 1773-1818
Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
Franklin, William, 1731-1813
Hewson, M. S., (Mary Stevenson)
Hosack, Mary Eddy Wistar
Livingston, William, 1723-1790
Randolph, Thomas M., (Thomas Mann), 1768-1828
Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Accessioned 4/--/1938. See in-house shelf list for accession numbers and dates.
Early American History Note
The Bache Family collection contains a range of letters from members of the extended Franklin-Bache family, descendants of Benjamin Franklin. Although the vast majority are from the early republic, there are some papers from the twentieth century that involve Franklin’s legacy (the collection appears to have been acquired by the APS in 1938). Among the correspondence included are letters to and from Benjamin Franklin Bache, William Temple Franklin, Sarah Franklin Bache, Richard Bache, William Bache and Catherine Wistar Bache.
The papers reflect miscellaneous correspondence to and from this very prominent and important American family. Many of the letters are personal in nature and involve correspondence amongst members of the extended family about their lives. There are other significant collections of such correspondence in the papers of William Temple Franklin, Sarah Franklin Bache, and Benjamin Bache Franklin at the APS. Nonetheless, this miscellaneous collection does provide a portrait of family relations in the early national period for both those within the extended Bache family and for those writing to the Bache’s about their own family affairs. The collection has a notable number of women letter writers who often relate their daily life and family affairs.
A letter from Richard, one of the Benjamin Franklin Bache’s sons, to his mother Sarah captures the intimacy of many of these letters. The long letter recounts a game the children played with the children of family friends. The game involved sticking needles into a burning candlestick at midnight to find out who one’s future spouse would be. When the children did it, one of the older children came into the room wearing a sheet to look like a ghost and frightened the younger children. Among the more interesting items is a letter from William Franklin to his sister Sarah Franklin Bache in 1794. Although Benjamin Franklin disowned his son, the two siblings kept in contact, as evidenced by this correspondence. The collection also contains a significant portion of correspondence from the 1830s and 1840s from less prominent members of the Bache family writing about their lives.
There are scattered documents from the late-nineteenth century and early twentieth century. Of particular note are a series of letters discussing the family’s attempt to take control of Benjamin Franklin’s Trust that he had left to Boston and Philadelphia for charity. Around 1890, some of Franklin descendants tried to reclaim approximately $450,000 Franklin left to charity, and these documents consist of the family’s organizing efforts and legal strategies. The collection also contains the wills of Richard and Benjamin Franklin Bache and two genealogical collections from the 1870s that trace out the descendants of Sarah Franklin Bache.
A note on the correspondents: Richard Bache, an immigrant from England who had worked as a merchant in New York and then Philadelphia, married Franklin’s daughter Sarah (Sally). Benjamin Franklin was at first displeased with the marriage, but eventually accepted it. The Bache’s had a number of children. Benjamin Franklin Bache, their first child, became a favorite of Franklin’s, and he traveled to Europe with Franklin during the American Revolution.
Richard Bache served in a number of prominent organizations during his time in Philadelphia, including postmaster general during the American Revolution. He went into business with the Shippens and Willings, served on Revolutionary committees, and was a Director at the Bank of North America.
Sarah Franklin Bache, called Sally, was a politically active Philadelphian who supported the American Revolution by serving in voluntary associations and later supported the Democratic-Republicans, advising her son Benjamin Franklin Bache on political matters. She was also a close confidante of her father. The family lived with him and assisted him in his old age. The Bache’s had eight children, among them Benjamin Franklin Bache and William Bache (a doctor who married Catherine Wistar), all of whom have letters in this collection.
William Temple Franklin was the illegitimate son of Franklin’s illegitimate – and eventually disowned – son, William Franklin. William Temple, like Benjamin Franklin Bache, traveled to France with his grandfather. William, however, played a far more important role while there. While Benjamin Franklin Bache was just a child at the time, William Temple served as Franklin’s aide and was eventually appointed Secretary to the America delegation at the Treaty of Versailles. He later published Franklin’s papers, which were given to him as part of his inheritance.
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Family Correspondence; Genealogies.; General Correspondence; Journalists -- Pennsylvania.; Law; Legal Records; Marriage and Family Life; Miscellaneous; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs.; Physicians -- Pennsylvania.; Printing and Publishing; United States - Armed Forces - Medical care; United States - Armed Forces - Medical personnel; United States - History - 1783-1865; United States - History - Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States - History - Revolution - 1775-1783 - Personal narratives; Wills.; Women's History
- Papers
  - Letter to Mrs. [Sarah Franklin] Bache, Philadelphia, Aug. 25, 1770; B B121; 9x7-1/2; Hewson, M. S. (Mary Stevenson)
    Scope and Contents note
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. Friendly letter. Concerning B.Franklin. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.1
  - Letter to [Mrs. Sarah Franklin Bache], Aug. 16, 1771; B B121; 9x7-1/4; Hewson, M. S. (Mary Stevenson)
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Birth of William Hewson. Refers to B.Franklin. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.2
  - Letter to Gov. Livingston, Trenton, Jan. 15, 1782; B B121; 9 1/2" x 7 3/4"; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Phila., A.L.S. 1p. and add. Has ordered the post round the mountain by Veal Town, thus evading Clinton's party. Birth of the Dauphin. Previously cataloged as B B121.1
  - Letter to Mrs. [Sarah] Bache, April 12, 1783; B B121; 6 1/2" x 8 1/4"; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Passy, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Seal. Introduces the bearer, Mr. Mason.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Sarah Franklin] Bache, July 26, 1783; B B121; 9x7-1/4; Montgomery, Dorcas?
    Paris, A.L.S.with initials. 3p.and add. ----Photostat of c.of L. 2p. On same sheet is letter from C. Greene to [S.Bache]; Aug.20,1785. (from Yale university library, in Miscellaneous manuscript collection:Film 54-65 Frame 87.) Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.3
  - Letter to William Bache, Dec. 27, 1783; B B121; 7 1/4" x 9"; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798
    Passy, A.L.S. 1p. and add. His last letter contained a long description of the air balloons.
  - Letter to William Bache, April 7, 1790; B B121; 6 1/2" x 8 1/4"; Bache, Theophylact, 1735-1807
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Family news; hopes his grandfather [B. Franklin] is free from pain.
  - Letter to [Mrs.] Richard Beach [Sarah Franklin Bache], Philadelphia, May 31, 1790; B B121; 9x7-3/4; Redick, David
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add. Condolences for death of B.Franklin. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.4
  - Letter to Mrs. Sarah [Franklin] Bache, Philadelphia, Nov. 17, 1791; B B121; 10x8-1/4; Markoe, Peter, 1752?-1792
    St.Croix, A.L.S. 2P.and add. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.5
  - Letter to [Mrs.] Catharine Wistar [Bache], Philadelphia, Oct. 1, 1793; B B121; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Hosack, Mrs. Mary Eddy
    New York, A.L.S.with initials. 2p.and add.,end. Friendly letter. Concerning yellow fever in Philadelphia. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.6
  - Letter to William Bache, London, June 28, 1794; B B121; 9-3/4x7-1/2; Markoe, Fr
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.: "Care of William Franklin." Enc.wanting. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.7
  - Letter to William Bache, London, Aug. 9, 1794; B B121; 9-1/2x8; Markoe, Fr
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.: "Care of William Franklin." Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.8
  - Letter to Mrs. Sarah Bache, Aug. 23, 1794; B B121; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    London, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Has introduced William to Dr. Johnson and others; hopes to make him acquainted with Dr. Ingenhous. Glad to hear of their escape from the dreadful disorder at Philadelphia.
  - Letter to William Bache, Sept. 20, 1794; Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. Family news; yellow fever. With sketch of woman
  - Letter to Richard Bache, Sept. 8, 1795; B B121; 7 1/2" x 9"; Bache, William, 1773-1818
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Family.
  - Letter to [Mrs.] Catharine Wistar [Bache], Philadelphia, Aug. 4, 1796; B B121; 10x8; Hosack, Mrs. Mary Eddy
    New York, A.L.S.with initials. 3p.and add.,end. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.9
  - Letter to [Mrs.] Catharine Wistar [Bache], New York, Nov. 21, 1796; B B121; 10x8; Hosack, Mrs. Mary Eddy
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 2p.and add.,end. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.10
  - Letter to Dr. [William] Bache, May 7, 1798; B B121; 6 1/2" x 8"; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Settle, A.L.S. 1p. Encloses the "conclusion of your grandfather's instructions to me, on his going to France in...1776" for Mr. Niemcewicz (?).
  - Letter to William Bache, Philadelphia, May 30, 1798; B B121; 10x8; Gahn, Henry
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no. 11
  - Letter to Mrs. S[arah] Bache, April 2, 1799; B B121; 6 1/2" x 8"; Bache, Richard, 1784-1848
    Burlington, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Family.
  - Letter to Mrs. Catherine Bache, July 12, 1799; B B121; Ryerss (?), H
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Catherine] Bache, April 21, 1800; B B121; Cooper, Hannah
    (?). Fragment of A.L.S. portion of p. and add.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Sarah] Bache, May 5, 1801; B B121; 7 1/2" x 9"; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Settle, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Family.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Catharine Wistar] Bache, Jan. 28, 1803; B B121; 9x7-1/2; Trist, Mrs. Mary Brown
    Philadelphia; Pen Park, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.16
  - Letter to W[illia]m Bache, Oct. 29, 1805; B B121; 8" x 10"; Randolph, Thomas M. (Thomas Mann), 1768-1828
    Monticello, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Legal matters.
  - Letter to Catharine [Bache], Aug. 16, 1807; B B121; 8" x 10"; Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808
    Settle, A.L.S. 1p. Family.
  - Letter to Sally Bache, Aug. 22, 1807; B B121; 6 1/2" x 8 1/4"; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Settle, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Family.
  - Letter of administration for Benjamin Franklin's estate, Dec. 2, 1807; B B121.3 no.1; 13x8; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Rich[ard] Bache, W[illiam] Bache and Rich[ard] Bache, Jr. Witnessed: J.Wampole. 2p., end. (see Bache family papers)
  - Letter to [ ] Wister, Aug. 15, 1808; B B121; 6 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Wister, E H
    Cotness, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Mutilated
  - Will, Jan. 2, 1810; B B121.w; 15 1/2" x 10"; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Settle, Pa. A.D. 7p. and end. Mutilated, signature cut away. Att: Aug. 2, 1811. Mentions Dr. Benjamin Franklin. Deposited by the Register of Wills Office, Phila; Dec. 10,1954 - restricted, cf. terms of use, Legal folder. See Bound Volume, Floor E. ---- Photostat of copy of D. 9p. Presented by E.M. Riley, Jan.1951.
    General note
    Not found 5/2011
  - Renunciation of the administration of the estate of Benjamin Franklin, Aug. 26, 1811; B B121.3 no.2.; 7x8; Bache, William, 1773-1818
    Philadelphia, D.S.: W.Bache Louis Bache and Rich[ard] Bache. 1p.and end. Register: Samuel Bryan. (see Bache family papers)
  - Letter of administration for Benjamin Franklin's estate, Aug. 27, 1811; B B121.3 no.3; 12-1/2x7-3/4; Sergeant, Thomas, 1782-1860
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: T.Sergeant, Louis Bache and Rich[ard] Bache. Witnessed: Sam.Bryan. 2p.,end. (see Bache family papers.)
  - Letter to Mrs. [Catharine Wistar] Bache, Philadelphia, May 15, 1812; B B121; 10x8; Hosack, Mrs. Mary Eddy
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.12
  - Letter to Catherine Bache, July 11, 1813; B B121; 8" x 10"; Wistar, Thomas
    A.L.S. 1p. and add.
  - Letter to Catharine Bache, Oct. 12, 1814; B B121; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Wistar, Bartholomew, 1790-1841
    Phila., A.L.S. 2p. and add.
  - Letter to Catharine Bache, July 1, 1816; B B121; Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
    Roxborough, A.L.S. 2p. and add.
  - Letter to Mrs. Catharine [Wistar] Bache, Princeton, Oct. 17, 1816; B B121; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Trist, E
    Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.13
  - Letter to Mrs. Catharine [Wistar] Bache, Princeton, Jan. 23, 1817; B B121; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Hosack, Mrs. Mary Eddy
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.and add., end. Friendly letter. Concerning G. Morris' death and his wife. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.14
  - Letter to --, March 3, 1818; Wistar, Elizabeth.
    A.L.S. 2p.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Catharine Wistar] Bache, Philadelphia, Sept. 13, 1820; B B121; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Jones, M
    New Orleans, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Seal Friendly letter. Previously cataloged as B B121.2 no.15
  - Letter to William Meredith, Jan. 8, 1821; James, Thomas C., (Thomas Chalkley), 1766-1835
    A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Concerning estate of Mrs. Sarah Bache: has been asked to be Guardian to Catharine Bache.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Meredith, Oct. 16, 1821; Morris, Mathias
    Doylestown, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning Mrs. Bache's Estate.
  - Letter to John Wister, Nov. 26, 1830; B B121; 8" x 12 3/4"; Mallory, G
    wilkes Barre, A.L.S. 1p. and add.
  - Letter to C. G. McChesney, Hights Town, New Jersey, Aug. 20, 1834; Bache, William
    Wellsboro Tioga, A.L.S. 1p.and add. Thanks for communication, and is thankful for his long healthy life.
  - Letter to H.G. Upham, Nov. 3, 1852; B B121; 4 3/4" x 7 1/4"; Marcy, William L. (William Learned) 1786-1857
    Albany, A.L.S. 2p.
  - Tho[ma]s Hewson Bache to John Bigelow, 1867 Nov 18
    Photocopy
  - Tho[ma]s Hewson Bache to John Bigelow, 1868 April 27
  - Republican National Convention Delegate's Ticket., June 16, 1896
    1 ticket for St. Louis convention.
  - Letter to William Bache, Undated; B B121; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Bache, Elizabeth Franklin, 1777-1820
    Tuesday morning. A.L.S. 1p. and add.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Sarah ?] Bache, Undated; B B121; 8" x 8 1/4"; Vaughan, Sarah
    n.d. A.L.S. 2p. and add.
  - Letter to Catherine Wistar, Undated; B B121; W., H S
- Series Two: Material related to Benjamin Franklin Bache
  Benjamin Franklin Bache (1801-1881); Primarily related to Benjamin Franklin Bache's time as surgeon of the Navy before and during the Civil War.
  - Certificate of merit to Benjamin F. Bache., Oct. 28, 1842; La Sociedad Medica de Emulacion de Barcelona.
    Printed D. Mss filled in. 1p.
  - Agreement made between Bache of the City of New York and Charles G. Taylor, etc., June, 1856
    A.D. 1p.
  - Letter to B.F. Bache, Sept. 9, 1865; U.S. Navy
    A.L.S.: Chief of Bureau; granting leave for Bache.
  - Letter to Thomas Hart, Jr., April 27, 1868; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1801-1881
    A.L.S. 3p.
  - Letter to Benjamin F. Bache, June 14, 1868; Porter, Daniel D.
    A.L.S. 5p.
  - General order, no. 159, Aug. 29, 1870; U.S. Navy
    T.D. order an "Act to further promote teh efficiency of the Navy"
  - US Secretary of the Navy to BF Bache, 1870 Sept 13
  - US Navy General order, no. 163, 1871 Sept 1
  - Letter to B.F. Bache, Sept. 18, 1871; U.S. Navy
    A.L.S.: Acting Secretary Navy; "In accordance with General Order No 163, you will regard yourself detached from duty in charge of the Naval Laboratory at New York on the 1st October next, proceed to your home and wait orders."
  - Letter to B.F. Bache, Feb. 1, 1873; U.S. Navy
    1p. Commissions Bache Medical Director.
  - Invitation to Miss Jeannie L. Bache, Oct. 27, 1876
    Printed. 1p. Mss filled in. Invitation to the International Exhibition of 1876 at Fairmount Park, Philalphia.
  - Ticket of admission to International Exhibition closing Ceremonies, Nov. 10, 1876
  - Will, June 3, 1879; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1801-1881
    A.D. 3p.
  - Certification as to the will of B.F. Bache, Dec. 23, 1881; State of New York. Surrogates Court. County of Kings.
    Printed D. Mss. filled in. 1p.
  - Outline statement of counsel in regard to the Franklin trusts, May 28, 1890; Duane, Russell, 1866-; Pepper, George Wharton, 1867-1961
  - Concerning a proposed suit to recover funds from Benjamin Franklin's estate, May 28, 1890; Gillespie, E. D. (Elizabeth Duane), b. 1821; Irwin, Sophia A.
    A.D. 5p.
  - Letter to William S. Gould, June 7, 1890; Biddle, A. Sydney
    1p. conerning B. Franklin's will.
  - Letter to William S. Gould, June 7, 1890; Duane, Russell, 1866-
    A.L.S. 2p. concerns Franklin's will.
  - Letter to "Dear Aunt Jeannie" [L. Bache], Dec. 7, 1923
    T.L. 2p. signed "Ed"
  - Extracts from my mother's will, Undated; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1801-1881